Well, welcome.
We've got a really a baker's
dozen already in here.
And with just a minute to go
until start time, it's
nice to see some old friends
and and to recognize names of folks
I haven't met.
And.
Yeah, if it's all right with everybody,
I'll just get things rolling.
Take it away.
Thank you very much.
Hey, my name is Robert “Bobby” Arellano.
I also write when I write hypertext
and illit with the mouse name
Bobby Rabbit.
And I'm here to talk about sunshine.
6930 years ago this summer,
the first web novel went live.
And.
Folks naturally asked me about
and comment on the first claim.
And that is part of the story there.
By all means were remarkable
electronic works before sunshine 69,
but this was the first web
born hypertext novel
to call itself a novel
specifically for for the web
and written in story
space exported to HTML.
You'll hear more about that
in just a moment in my discussion
with Scott Redbrick.
Although for me, part of the process
and I can imagine I'm not the only person
who, six months before a conference, sees
an opportunity to submit an idea
for a panel or a paper presentation
and kind of gets down to work
after getting their abstract submitted.
And one of the big unknowns for me,
when I pitched an idea
to talk about sunshine 69,
in just a very intimate one
on one with Scott
Berg on its 30th anniversary was,
I wasn't sure what all I had
in terms of archive
and or multimedia materials
that related to it.
I had a box
that had moved with me across the country,
and then several moves
between home bases after that,
and I didn't open it up
until just a few weeks ago.
And what I found was really a treasure
of adjacent materials
to the sunshine 69 web novel
that were in print were in video, audio,
actual film camera, film negatives.
And just for one example,
something I'll show you
in a better resolution in just a moment.
Printouts of various drafts
of sunshine 69,
like this one with my teacher and mentor
at the time, Robert Coover.
Some of you know about him
will mention him a little more.
Robert Cooper's handwriting
in red in that case.
And in the next hour or so, we're going
to talk about what else was in the box.
Plus, I think I could really
use the help of someone in this room,
not sure who it's going to be yet in
making sense of some of that marginalia
that Robert Coover wrote,
because some of it's in very
his very proprietary
form of penmanship and also water damaged.
And I've had dog eared
and torn versions of what I'm
trying to collect now in the sunshine
69 collection of materials.
So I'm going to start by
letting a video play
that's just 17 minutes long.
It's that conversation
between me and Scott Redbird
that we figured was,
you know, best for a variety of reasons
time change and technical
challenges to pre-record.
And that also let me drop in my slides.
So it's kind of nice.
I really after the video,
if you'll bear with me and you know,
you can snack and keep your mic muted
and hopefully get most of what you need
out of this quick conversation
presentation, we will return to the room
and and just have a conversation
in the gallery style.
And I definitely invite you to use
the chat while the video is playing.
I'll be able to monitor.
It is a nice thing to about having
had my my prep, my conversation with Scott
prerecorded itself
and an asynchronous prep
for this asynchronous conference.
That's just really been so exciting for us
for the last few days.
And by the way, I just, you know,
I can't say how much I really appreciate
anesthesia.
PD anyone else who's been involved
in making this one of the smoothest
and most enjoyable online
conferences I've ever been a part of,
and also the other presenters.
I went to a great talk by Dini here
and colleagues at WSU
Vancouver the other day
about archives and preservation,
and that's exactly what this one
project instance is about.
So as I share my screen now
and let the video roll
and make sure I share with sound,
I'll also drop later
a link in the chat
to just the YouTube version of this video.
I'm playing it off of
the QuickTime player on my
laptop and optimizing for video sharing,
so hopefully you receive it
almost as as good
without too much buffering resolution
as you would YouTube video
over this zoom call right now.
So as I start to share a screen
for that, keep an eye out for
a machine shaped like a bicycle.
Some of the comments
that Robert covers red pen notations
actually proposed for this first
novel web novel in HTML
and for a mouse,
not the peripheral,
but an animal, a plush mouse.
And the role it played in a kind of
an early.
Tangential project to the sunshine
69 novel.
So here comes my screen share,
and I'm going to play this,
and you can let me know
if anyone has trouble
by commenting in the chat,
but otherwise I think
I should just make sure I've muted myself
and let this play.
Enjoy this 17 minutes and the slides
with an additional visual aid
that will hopefully give you a better idea
of what sunshine 69 looks like,
and what some of the archive
that I'm digging up looks like.
Starts
at about five minutes in and continues out
into the last part
of this very brief video.
Here it comes.
So. Hey, Bobby.
Hey, Scott.
Sorry I couldn't be there
for the actual panel discussion,
but we're doing this here a little bit
before the ELO 2026 conference.
And I guess this is sort of a birthday
party. Yes.
Happy birthday, sunshine 6930 years.
And thank you, Scott,
for being my interlocutor on this day.
Sunshine, 69, was the first web born
hypertext novel to call itself a novel,
a built in story
space exported into HTML, integral
to the World Wide Web.
That's what we're celebrating the moment
the web first
imagined a novel in its own language.
With sunshine 69, you can watch a literary
form inventing itself.
The choices are still visible,
the floors are still visible,
the architecture is still there.
And every year a new round of readers
finds it for the first time.
Yeah, and story
space was for for people who don't know.
But I think a lot of people in ello will.
But it was a pre web
hypertext fiction system.
Storage space is a pre web spatial
hypertext writing environment developed
by a J.
David Bolter, Michael Joyce
and John B Smith, with Mark Bernstein
carrying it forward
through Eastgate Systems to this day.
Less than a year ago, I wrote the
Living Glossary of Digital Narrative
entry on Story
Space and interviewed Mark
so I could get that lineage exactly right.
The idea to publish sunshine
69 online was lucky timing.
That year.
Leading up to it was the first year
a version of Story Space
was released
that exported directly into HTML.
Hypertext suddenly wasn't trapped inside
specialized software anymore.
I wanted the novel to be born
where readers already lived.
HTML still here, and the novel
is still readable 30 years later.
Yeah, and I think part of the reason
why you're doing this, in addition
to sort of having a birthday party,
is that you sort of unearthed an archive
of both, sort of your own materials,
but things around them some.
Robert Coover,
of course, was was one of your
or perhaps your main writing teacher
at the time that you were writing
sunshine 69
so why don't you take me back there
to Brown University?
What was it?
When did you start this thing?
1994.
The earliest version of sunshine 69
was titled Altamont,
with an anarchy symbol.
Standing in for that first letter
a two years earlier.
That was my MFA thesis at Brown.
It was completed in 1994,
maybe about a 10th of what
the finished sunshine
69 novel would become.
As far as I know,
it was the first master's thesis
in any department
submitted electronically,
but the writing itself began earlier
in Robert Cooper's very first
hypertext
fiction workshop in January of 1991.
By 93, I was already publishing online
a zine called Albert Hofmann's
Strange Mistake.
On the 50th anniversary
of the first acid trip.
It was distributed over FTP servers
with fetch.
I remember being away.
People would download the Story
Space reader, a sunshine 69.
You know, it really grew up
alongside the web itself.
Sonic net serialized it one passage
a day from June through December of 96.
Yeah, and there's a lot of wonderful
characters in this in this novel,
many based on real historical figures
or kind of shadow historical figures
as well.
But, you know, the Glimmer Twins.
Yeah.
Who are, you know, Rolling Stones? Yeah.
Make an appearance.
Timothy Leary is in there.
Twins.
Keith and Mick had missed out on Woodstock
a few months prior,
and this was the stones
attempt at restitution.
A free concert, their own Woodstock
West, staged in December
at a stock car speedway on the East Bay.
But instead of being peace and love,
it became what some still call
the death of the 60s.
Yeah, there's what happened at Altamont to
begin with and maybe, maybe unfold that.
Let me tell you about what happened
in 1969 at Altamont Speedway,
while the Rolling Stones performed,
Meredith Hunter, an 18 year old black
man, was stabbed to death
under the stage lights
by Alan Passaro,
a Hells Angel from one of the clubs
that Stone's management
had retained his security.
The Hells Angels
Motorcycle Club paid in $500 worth of beer
inject on this scene
thousands of bad acid trips due
to someone who distributed free doses,
which many chroniclers of that period say
was not LSD at all,
but a psychosis inducing experimental drug
developed by the CIA for the purpose
of disrupting the anti-war counterculture.
So a hit of orange sunshine handed to you
at Altamont would make you feel
crazy enough that you weren't sure
it was ever going to end.
Meredith Hunter entered my novel.
Alan Passaro entered the novel.
Alongside them came fictional lives
that I created
for the sake of the narrative norm,
the Vietnam veteran.
Orange sunshine,
the girl named after the acid.
Or perhaps it was the acid
that was named after her, and then
a double agent of a character operating
under two aliases, Ronald Stark and Corey
Ali, a goblin winding his way
through the crowd at Altamont,
distributing
doses of the adulterated orange sunshine.
A final character who I gave voice
to was Lucifer, who needs no introduction.
During spring break, I flew to California
and spent hours in Alameda
County Courthouse copying the trial
transcript for $0.05 a page.
The defense exhibits
included a dressmaker's dummy showing
every stab wound and the knife itself
still bloodstained during the summer
and fall of 96, the serialization ran
a passage a day on Sonic Net.
It was kind of a small blip
on the cultural radar at the time.
Then something unexpected happened.
Readers began writing into the story.
Someone claimed to know Orange Sunshine.
Someone else had known Pissarro.
There was even someone who said
she was Meredith Hunter's sister.
Suddenly,
the novel had grown a life outside itself.
The guestbook has stayed open
for more than half of the last 30 years,
but server
migration has knocked it out for a while,
and that's one reason
I want to restore the guestbook here.
On the anniversary.
The first visitor signed it in 96, and
I'd like to see the next generation
writing entries.
We're also bringing back
the eight track deck, an audio player
from the original soundtrack recordings
by Will
Oldham, Colin Gagan and myself
under the name Bobby Rabbit.
The music lived on the site from the very
beginning in old real audio files,
and now it's being
remastered as wave and MP3.
Oh, and the novel toured.
I'd set sunshine 69,
running on a projector from a laptop,
while a big plush mouse,
the animal, not the peripheral, was passed
through the audience.
Whoever held it chose the next link.
I called them High Performance.
Kate Hayles reminded me that she saw one
at DAC Digital Arts
and Culture conference
at Georgia Tech in 1999.
One one of the interesting things
is in that early story,
you actually shaped the tax
like like a bicycle,
and you were thinking about this
sort of this architecture
and different ways that people
would navigate a textual space.
Thank you for coming in on that.
The original Altamont title
screen is already the novel in miniature.
A bright red Anarky A doubles
as a bicycle wheel sitting on a stretch
of blue pavement with a yellow center line
and a long black skid mark beneath it.
Zoom into the story space, map itself,
and you discover
the entire architecture is literally
shaped like a bicycle.
The rear wheel carries Bobby's childhood.
The front wheel carries
the Altamont concert.
Between them sits a derailleur,
not just links, but lexia
that can turn a reader's
point of view into another gear.
Eventually, the bicycle grew into the four
wheeled sunshine 69 Rambler convertible.
That's still the splash page today.
And the calendar
the Bay area map of the suitcase.
These are the three main ways in.
In Altamont,
ten year old Bobby Rabbit is a boy
haunted by a year he never lived through.
He was too young to remember 1969,
old enough to inherit its aftershocks
as he keeps brooding over
what happened when his older brothers
and sisters were his age.
He writes deeper and deeper
into those histories until he flies off
his bicycle in a moment of distraction.
After flying off the bike, Bobby's
crash becomes a seam into another world
of the summer of 69, and Meredith Hunter
and other consciousnesses.
And you showed me
some documents
that I thought were really interesting,
some commentary from Coover,
and I note the notes you sent me.
You said, like Coover is a co-op.
That was really interesting
because, like, you can tell how invested
and how sort of excited in
a way, Coover got about these hypertext
and helping people to think through
what might be like.
I see some notes here, like, should
there be should there be a link here?
Yeah.
You know, maybe cut this, move this
to another, move this to another space.
Think about how you're connecting
the authors together.
For as long as I knew Robert Coover,
he wanted to read on paper
with a pen in his hand.
So I printed every passage
of Altamont and later
sunshine 69,
and literally placed the pages before him.
That's why his annotations exist
three complete readings, three different
pen colors, three different stages
of the work, and states of attention.
He commented at every scale,
from individual words to the overall
architecture.
One notice stayed with me for 35 years,
he said.
You're actually creating an acid trip here
with hypertext.
At the time, I heard the psychedelic
reference, but years later I realized he's
meaning something deeper.
He wasn't just describing
subject matter,
he was identifying a compositional method.
The form itself was dissolving
boundaries between people, time
periods and perspectives.
The architecture was performing
the same shifts in consciousness
that the prose described.
Shelly Jackson
was there right around the same time.
And she did.
Let's see, she did.
She did her hypertext starting in.
And do you remember
when her hypertext fictions came out?
Shelley Jackson
wrote the first draft of Patchwork Girl
for one of George Lando's
courses at Brown in 9394.
Eastgate published it in 1995,
the year before
sunshine 69 went up,
which means we were in workshop together.
The first year
I was finishing sunshine 69.
Patchwork
girl was developing almost simultaneously.
I had also been George Lando's research
assistant that summer,
updating the Victorian web to HTML.
If we kind of look at it historically now,
the moments of web hypertext
was relatively brief, you know,
in terms of the span of of our lives,
although I think a lot of things
were taken away from web hypertext,
maybe even not only
in electronic literature, but into wider
aspects of, of the culture as,
as the web evolved,
where do you think
what what what became of hypertext?
I've taught a course called
writing Non-linear more than 20 times over
the past ten years at Southern Oregon,
and my students are composing entwine
free, open in the browser or the direct
descendant of what story space started.
My students published to the Interactive
Fiction database
and dig through the communities
around the IFR for new Elit games,
and we still use the ello directory
to find the classics,
their gamers, their dad players.
One student
recently said about the Hypertext Hotel
that it reminded her of the web
before it got overtaken by trolls.
The week we
recorded this, a note arrived from Sue
Koonin, a professor in Iowa
who's been teaching sunshine 69 to college
students for 21 years straight.
It's her bridge text from Princeton
to electronic literature,
and she's found even readers who struggle
with more open ended hypertext
her, in her phrase, way happier
with the organized chaos of sunshine.
69 the calendar, the map,
the suits as metaphors and mechanisms.
Sue kindly shared her intro lecture
slides, which I point to from here.
Robert Coover,
who died in 2024, used to say he wasn't
expecting the great American
hypertext novel, but that students in his
workshops would approach any writing
differently for the rest of our lives.
And it's true, everything I wrote
after was affected by it, which is why
all of my novels are experimental in time
space point of view.
Cosmic books
published my first novel, fast,
Steady and Good Old Book Form,
in the summer of 2001.
Every print novel
since then has carried the.
DNA of sunshine.
69 Havana Lunar.
I composed like a Rubik's Cube,
shifting chapters through time
and between points of view
right up to the final draft.
Don, daimyo of La
Plata, splices its narrator's voice
across registers the
way a link splices lexia.
The question remains exactly the same
whether we're talking about
HTML or VRR or print.
What is a story in this environment,
and how do I shape
a literary experience for someone?
The decisions behind sunshine 69 exist
in exactly three places the work itself,
a dossier here in Oregon,
and one living memory
that can still explain the relationships.
Yeah, and I think that's so important.
I mean, I think it's also important to go
on, keep inventing,
keep creating, keep making new things.
But there's also these boxes
that you find.
Right.
And like you literally found
a box of things at the early development
of your work
and with a lot of material related
to things like where Robert Cooper's ideas
came up about this.
So I think it's so important now, too,
that people like Dean Gregory,
the work that she's doing on the next.
And I was just talking
for her about the town Mehmet
archive that they're doing there,
but that we're finding
institutional homes
and that we're having these conversations
about the
the early period of electronic literature.
So that and hopefully people will study
it, learn from it,
make more interesting things
as a result of engaging with it.
Absolutely. Couldn't have said it better.
And cheers to our colleagues
in the Electronic Literature organization
for carrying the torch, keeping the flame.
Well, I got to go because I'm in Denmark
and it's like, time for for dinner.
Yeah, but it's been, like,
really great talking with you, Bobby.
And I'll be having breakfast here
in Oregon.
Congratulations
on outliving the 30th anniversary of.
Oh, and here's the strange thing.
Scott Sunshine, 69, is now
older than I was when I wrote it.
For whatever that's worth.
So you're just a spring chicken?
Well put. Thank you. Scott.
If you
just joined us, that was the prerecorded
conversation
that Scott and I had in preparation
for this panel.
We just decided to make it
so that I could throw the slides in there
and Swift and 17 minutes,
and I'll share a link to
that as a separate YouTube,
although I know it'll be in the
conference repository as well.
But I saw a few good comments
and questions in the chat.
I invite people to continue
to use the chat,
whether for direct comments to me
or just conversation with each other.
I thought I would try to zoom in.
So before we have more of a gallery
kind of conversation
on one page from the
oh, I'm
just suddenly
going to call it the Coover Codex.
And if you're not familiar
with Robert Coover, by the way,
I think I can just drop this in the chat
to for anyone
who wants to zoom in a little closer.
Yeah, we'll do that.
Alrighty. And.
You're always
welcome to speak up on the mic now, too.
There's just about 20 of us in here,
so that's easy for me to.
If I'm not able to see you
or for whatever reason,
you just have a question
that you want to catch my attention.
Thank you. Deanie.
And then right there next to Denise
comment is this exact same page
that I'm sharing on the screen right now,
inviting
anyone who either wants to download it
on their own, or just kind of
lean as close as you can to
your monitor to help me figure out what
that notation
on the left side of the page is in Robert
Cooper's very distinctive red penmanship,
I see.
Nice pair.
And then underneath that,
can she have any role at all?
But I, I've never been able
to make out that blotch.
And, and this is one of dozens of examples
of comments
that Coover made that
I'm sort of trying to parse.
Now that I did open the dossier,
I'm going to call it,
I wrote a contribution to the proceedings,
where I go into a little more detail
about the experience
of finding these materials.
So for a lot of you,
it may be your first introduction
to sunshine 69.
And some of you may have questions
about Robert Coover, who, as I mentioned,
died in 2024,
a kind of an original founder,
along with Scott Berg and others
of the Electronic Literature Organization,
had held some conferences at Brown
as well as taught
the first hypertext fiction
workshops there 35 years ago.
And and maybe just in preparation
for any conversational questions,
I'll mention that the.
The three things that
I'm really still working on this summer,
thanks to the getting
the fire Stoked Under Me by ELO 26,
are restoration of the guest book,
as I mentioned in the conversation
with Scott, so that people can write
into sunshine 69 the same way
they did in 1996.
The eight track player,
which on that metaphor of the 69 Rambler
convertible
car, was the place that you could have
your tunes to ride
along with your ride
and through the story.
And the.
The other thing is that it made me
dig up earlier versions of Altamont,
the predecessor
to sunshine 69, as well as the zine
Albert Hofmann's Strange Mistake
that exists only on floppies.
So I'll probably need to work
with some folks,
travel up the tracks to Vancouver and see
if I can salvage any of those old story
space files that were the pre web
versions of sunshine 69,
as well as other projects
like Albert Hofmann's Strange Mistake.
So those are three things I'm thinking
about and working on this summer.
I love that, Deanie.
I know you're all set up for it.
The question I get
maybe most often from teachers
and in conversations with Sue,
who is the professor in Iowa
who's been teaching sunshine, 69,
for 21 years,
as well as just that, folks around ELO
who who ask
whether, you know, whether I think
sometimes 69 is appropriate
for particular reading groups.
I, I get the question a lot.
How do you know when you're finished
with a sprawling
many passages, over 300 passages
with, I think, 5000 link possibilities?
Just text links between them.
That's not counting the the menus
or the splash page, where you can
then go back to these more indexical
navigation mechanisms like the calendar,
the map, or the suitcase
full of character suits
that you try on to get in the story
that way.
And so folks ask how?
How do I teach it?
How do how do I know?
Or how does the reader,
the student, know when they're finished?
And I think that's something
that comes up for a lot of folks
working in electronic literature
today, as well as back in the day.
And probably each of us
have our own answers.
And and I've got a few
ideas for the way I.
Created the architecture for sunshine 69
that I think would go along
well with something like
the instructional videos
that Sue Kunin supplies for anyone
who thought they might want to include
sunshine, 69, or other early web
based works in their teaching,
in their conversations with students
in the year ahead, and I would love
to continue to make myself
available to you in that respect.
You know, as a fellow member of ELO, but
just as a guy with a email address here
at a university that you can reach out to
at any time and ask for the context
that I can give you
for your own teaching, for your own
scholarship, your own research.
But maybe I can pause there.
I don't have Scott here
to help me facilitate the Q&A as much,
but I am very happy
to either in the chat or just over
the mic,
see what kinds of questions arose,
whether just, you know, dates
and trying to help reconstruct
what happened
when and or any of my thoughts.
As one of the creators
of an early web work like that,
when I put together
sunshine 69, thank you very much.
Bobby.
If you were going to resurrect that in
for a contemporary audience.
Right.
Because we've shown it before.
Right?
We had in London at the Grand Tron event.
If you're going to reconstruct
that for a contemporary audience,
would you make any changes
to the interface to the art at all?
I'm just curious.
That's not like you should.
I'm just like, do would you want to?
And if not, why?
And if so, why?
I, you know.
I wouldn't mind creating a version
that would be almost like an adaptation, a
response text, its own project
that was perhaps more immersive.
We did that with the Hypertext Hotel,
which I know I'm now pulling yet
another early Brown University oriented
hypertext, although in that case
a collaborative
and asynchronous people worked on it
over years who never met and linked
to each other's stories, etc.
we made a VR version of that
just last year with a few students
using Unreal Engine five and blender and
and using VoiceOver as the the text.
So as you navigated through the lobby
and the bar,
the guest rooms, the pool of the hotel,
you heard
recorded voices narrating.
What was the story behind those rooms?
I could see trying something like that
with a small section of sunshine
69 or or a location from the map.
It would be a lot of fun.
It would be exciting for me.
Although for the most part, Dean,
I really love that
good old web 1.0 works still.
And for instance,
I like your I like your loss
and it was it a trick question
because I think it timestamps it
so beautifully, and yet at the same time
it gives off the idea of it
being psychedelic.
I can see an exhibition in the future
where we do all the psychedelic works
ever produce for ELO.
Yeah.
Yours, Colton, John McDaid.
I mean, there's
there's a handful of them, right?
You know, I think Johanna, I think so.
So much is not.
Yeah, so much is not actually
policed at the moment.
Although it went back and forth.
We had a couple of tricky years.
But yeah, the, the, the,
the early very pixelated,
you know,
it might have been, what, 72 dpi max
art and the fact
that it looks really chunky,
the pixels is weirdly
when I, when I demo it to students
who are in their late
teens or early 20s now, I now know there's
a kind of a fan
culture for pixel art thanks to them.
So it was kind of throw stuff
is so popular right now with my students.
They love Illit,
they love old elit especially.
That's so neat.
Thank you.
I wonder if and I wonder
if anyone else finds that.
I actually had a question
for the room myself, which maybe,
you know, in the 15 20 minutes or so
remaining and folks who can stick around.
I'm sure appreciate your kinship.
And, you know, your your curiosity.
What early Illit specifically web based
would be a nice way to start.
Do you teach any of you who teach
and or would you want to teach?
But there's something holding you back,
keeping you from from sharing it.
I mean, everything from I've had folks
maybe
who aren't on the coasts
as much in the universities
where I've been teaching at the last
10 or 15 years, who say, I don't want to.
I can't teach about anything that has
drug culture in it that I totally get.
In that case, there's lots of other things
instead of sunshine 69 but
but some folks just say, you know, well,
I, I don't know if my students
will spend as much time as they need to.
One benefit of sunshine 69.
After watching Leonardo's keynote
just an hour ago.
That I think is kind of interesting for us
as an option.
Is that because it's actually 300 or so
discrete HTML files living on a GitHub
that,
you know,
a person could find my repository,
but for the most part,
they'll just see the outward facing
top level
and a reader version of sunshine 69.
It would be very hard
to drop the whole thing into a chat
bot and say, write me a three page
paper on sunshine 69.
Yeah, you actually have
to click around in it at that point.
You might as well refining Bobby, is it
that in the lab is that
AI is not doing such a great job
with hypertext reading?
Awesome. I
thank you for that.
And you know, the teacher is here.
You are in the first round of,
you know, experience of
what do your students do
when you present them with something?
Or, you know, it could be a I know it's
it's not easy, but it could be a.
A more legacy
or excuse
me, story space style reader version.
Or some of us, like Dean, have HyperCard
running as good as the day
it was released.
And just to give you an example,
from my experience, I would love to teach
Patchwork Girl to my own
non-linear writing workshop students.
And yet, just for ease my own convenience,
I tend to use Shelley's companion
work, My Body
a Wonder Comer, because it's on the web
and and I don't know
what Shelley thinks about that.
I've reached out to Shelley once or twice
over the years,
haven't heard back as much recently, but
as I mentioned in the video with Scott,
we were workshop students together
and I still consider her a friend.
And thank you.
And now I'm looking and I'm
seeing really good comments in the chat.
I really appreciate the reference to,
for instance, looking up a little bit now.
The. Oh my gosh, I'm going to save this
whole chat.
This is fantastic.
The things that you teach like
jet, Jeff Richmond's 253
and that's wonderful to know
97 would have been around the
the publication
and also some published in 96.
Terrific uncle Roger and
thank you.
Richard, for that great question.
Yeah, we're just talking about that
hot off the press.
And I was there on Thursday.
I mean, the entire team up
at Washington State University,
Vancouver is not only doing, you know,
incredible.
Work preserving, but also the metadata.
The and it sounds like
some of the exhibitions now,
I just learned 15, 20 minutes ago
from Denny about one
that's going to be at the library, that's
going to have more ephemera involved.
And I just that to me is really exciting.
I'm, I'm hoping there will be
more opportunities to share the smudgy
manuscripts and, and the research
that happened at the courthouse
and the original analog
recordings of the soundtrack
and the old sunshine 69 plus plush
mouse toy that used to make its way
through the audience.
So people felt like they had a chance
to click and be the next person to choose
what was happening
in the public high performance.
I don't know if anyone sees anything
that I might have missed in the chat.
You can let me know.
But I also, I'm curious
if anyone else has any responses to do
you teach this stuff?
How and or what are the obstacles to
assigning
web born hypertext like this,
even if they are available,
even if you you do know
exactly where to find them
and they're alive on a website
somewhere.
I guess.
Yeah. Go ahead. Emily,
I guess the biggest hurdle for me
at this point,
because most of the courses I would teach
these in are just asynchronous online.
And so like the the hurdle is
like getting them to understand
what the web was like.
There was no web there.
You know, like you,
I try to talk to kids about,
oh, well, I remember before the internet
and I remember, you know,
hearing the dial up modem and it's like
it's just so much cultural context.
And then even with yours, you know,
going into the 60s and having, like,
you end up having to teach history
and technology and all these other layers
which inform the context
and help understand.
But it gets it's just it's just so much
I don't know.
Do you have any suggestions for that?
But be great.
Thank you. Emily. No. That's terrific.
You remind me of two things.
If you don't mind, I'll chime in.
And I'll invite Deanie
at any point to join me here.
We've taught together
and known each other for so many years.
And if I see.
By the way, just like when you teach,
if I see that you took off
your mute
like Jason, I'm going to call on you.
I take that as an indicator that you're.
You're thinking
of saying something or not.
It could have been a slippery.
But, Jason, I'll ask you to speak up.
You know, if you want.
Next to Emily's question, I see two
big areas that are sort of overlapping
in my Venn diagram of challenge, of
teaching that so much historical context.
And I do think Sue videos, which
I'll share again in the chat
in case anyone joined
after I had copy pasted that incredibly
do the job.
It's it's a 4 or 5 minute intro video
that just does enough
of reminding people what, say,
the historical context of the 60s
and the hippies and, and the,
you know, CIA
and the Vietnam War were about.
But your other big, you know,
sort of challenge as anyone's would be
is also just knowing that if you're
teaching online, if you're teaching
asynchronously, the students do,
they have the what it takes
to read an entire novel.
And I think that question,
as well as the question of what was 96
and the web like,
then that student who said,
wow, the hypertext hotel
was like the internet before trolls.
And by the way, that student was 19,
but they know that the internet was like.
And I sometimes tell people, they say,
how did they find sunshine 69?
I created a news
release that I sent to newspapers,
and I don't think if it hadn't been
for the Associated Press, the AP
picking it up, I wouldn't
have ended up in the LA times at the time.
And first the Providence Journal,
because I was there in, in Rhode Island
and, and I still saved
some of the old newspaper interviews
that kind of include
part of the experience of finding it.
There were only
there wasn't as much internet back then.
So folks
actually went somewhere to read a story
as one of my other short answers to that.
Thanks for reminding me, though.
That's a big challenge for the teachers
as well as the students.
Jason, did you have something you wanted
to add on the mic?
And I'll keep an eye on the chat to.
Yeah, I just wanted to say
one of the experiences that I always have
with students
trying to teach hypertext fiction
is they're they're so conditioned
to thinking of the hyperlink as a,
as an information seeking pathway.
Right. Then just click, click, click.
You know, I'm clicking on links
because I want to get to someplace where,
you know, I want to find this information.
It's like, no, you can't approach
hypertext links that way, right.
You have to kind of,
you know, stop, consider,
think about what you want to click on,
you know, and it's hard for them
to kind of break out of that.
So one of the reasons why I teach two,
five, three is
Reiman
says you can jump right to the end, right?
Just to the end of the story.
And then I said, well,
you can jump to the end of the story,
but then you're like, well,
what happened before the end?
And so encourages them to kind of,
you know, maybe be a bit more open
ended and exploratory.
So that's that's the one challenge
that I always find with hypertext
fiction is
you've got to get them to sort of
think about the hyperlink in a,
in a completely different way from what
they've grown up thinking about what
the hyperlink is for.
Great idea.
Thank you.
And in fact, you remind me I haven't
actually, except for a few screenshots
of this splash page
and the eight track player.
I haven't actually shown you
anything from sunshine 69 yet,
so I might try that trick.
Or at least suggest it and tell folks
go straight to December 6th.
Because sort of like some film students
might be.
Well, not anymore, but
I used to use the analogy of Pulp Fiction,
the Quentin Tarantino film.
If you're going to meet 7
or 8 different characters
and not know until the last scene
why you're meeting all these
seemingly disconnected characters,
they all converge in the last scene.
Similarly, sunshine 69 Everything
converges on December 6th
at the Altamont concert,
and I should invite students
to start there if you want to know.
And then you want to work backwards
and or jump around and find out
how the folks got there.
There's all these other
navigational mechanisms.
Well, great, great helpful suggestions.
Thank you.
And Deanie,
I remember that handout of internet sites
to visit it.
Bobby, I used to have
I don't know what happened to my copy.
It was stapled together and gave it to me
personally, I think it was at the 2002
state of the Arts.
That's that's where I think I got it.
And I have kept so much right.
And I, I've torn through my,
my office here.
I find everything else from,
from that conference except that document
just heartsick about it,
because I had used it so much.
Right, right, right.
And five pages long.
It was really short,
because that's all kind of all there was.
And it's really fun to
look at that document.
It's it has a website now,
but look at that in comparison
to what Mike Mandeville did
to download the internet.
Yeah.
Installation work that had, you know,
stacks and stacks and stacks of books
that he had downloaded the internet
and turned it into into books.
Yeah. That's right.
Look at the difference.
That's right.
What a difference.
I would love to read this book
about that.
And I'm no doubt that's something
someone's probably considering working on.
But, Gee, Deanie, I think down the line,
next time I get a sabbatical,
I'll just camp out across the river
there and then, you know, ask you
if we can chat a few coffee meetings
to have a
sort of a research
focused visit sometime
to, you know, the yellow, etc..
I have you in this exhibition
and be really great.
Wow. That's great. Thank you.
You gave me so many ideas
and I think both the hotel and I first
and foremost, the hotel would be exciting
to work on with you.
And then if room for sunshine 69 to Joe.
Johanna's good first, you know.
Yes, by all means, I,
I think I could bring back
the high performance
and I with the last 5 or 7 minutes here,
I actually wanted to make an offer
and that was even before your all's good.
Very warm and thoughtful as fellow
teachers as well as readers and writers.
Comments.
Which is that standing offer
from the next 360 days or so
until the 31st anniversary of sunshine 69.
If you end up teaching
or having a short section on sunshine
69 and one of your classes, I'll visit
in person if it's close enough.
Maybe with my mouse,
but but at least a zoom, right?
And we could have a conversation
with the students.
I could at least show
some of these same setup materials
and and really that that goes
for probably beyond next June.
But if you get to it
in the next 12 months,
I am a first come, first served.
Looking forward to visiting.
And I love I love chatting with students
from other institutions as well.
The the other good question, Johanna,
that you know, pardon me
if I've missed any in between was
did I ever have conversations
with Eastgate and Mark Bernstein,
who's still a friend?
And as I mentioned in the conversation
with Scott,
I got to write the the glossary,
the Living Glossary of Digital
Narrative or Electronic Literature.
It's hosted by
the center for Digital Narrative in Bergen
and the entry on Story Space.
I had a chance to interview Mark about.
And one of the things that really,
you know, I remember being a big deal
in 93, 94 was that story
space was pretty much contained
to publishing with a story space reader,
something that would be read on a disk.
But in fact, it was right around the time
I was getting into a sense of sunshine
69 reaching a whole finished
novel length, that they added
the affordance of export to HTML.
And I told Mark at the time,
I said, I am going to give credit to story
space everywhere I get the chance
as having been the authoring tool,
but I've been really looking at the web
and wanting to reach readers on the web.
So I'm going to take advantage of
your kind inclusion of this HTML export.
And we we agreed it was
it was the right thing to do with the work
at the time. Yes. Deanie.
When one of the challenges
with working with story space,
even the more tinderbox versions
that are exportable is that
it doesn't handle images,
especially color.
Mark was never interested in
that aspect of electronic literature,
right? Yes.
And so everything he's done,
even this most recent work, the
those Trojan girls, it's
a beautiful piece.
It's gorgeous, but it's black and white
and there's no images.
It's all text.
Because he was interested
in serious hypertext and serious hypertext
didn't have a lot of pictures.
Yes, exactly.
I remember those limitations.
And of course, you know, I didn't
I don't think video was possible at all.
And I don't know.
Yeah, that's right.
It's not multimedia.
The hypermedia of John McDade, uncle.
But funhouse you know, comes from the,
the, the little audio cassettes.
Yeah. Put into an audience.
That player wasn't embodied in the work
and they were images, but
they were bitmap
black and white, right? Yes.
Same for Shelley Jackson and Sarah
Smith's King of Space and Hyper Gate,
which he also produced.
So he just he wasn't he's not interested.
And he really is not wanting to
do publishing.
He wants to do he's a scientist.
Yeah.
That's right, that's right, that's right.
So I think there's other venues for you
to try maybe, you know, and you can,
but certainly it's a wonderful piece
and you don't need a you don't need it.
You don't need a publisher.
You've got your own folks, right.
You've got your audience. Right.
And thank you, by the way, for that link
to the Living Glossary
of digital narrative
right there in the chat, too.
And it's still growing.
And I think they're still looking
for people to write entries and work
our way backwards through some of the
the history as well as contemporary
entries that that need to
be written in that glossary.
Well, for as much as I kind of myself
wasn't sure
we'd have enough for a full hour,
it flew by.
And I missed any comments.
What a week we had.
And looking forward
to the final plenary
coming up in about 20 minutes, I think.
And then the awards.
So I'll stick around for a few.
But I really am grateful for all of you
for being here and by all means,
keep in touch, either
email at the university or in.
Now that I mentioned it,
I think it's about time for me
to make sure I'm back on the discord.
So I'll get I'll get on there
and make sure Bobby Rabbit
or Robert Arellano
or some hybrid version of us is on that.
Thank you very much.
Thank you. Richard. And thank you, Dini.
Thanks, Emily and PD and great
to see Talon and great to see Mark.
And I'll see you all in a little bit
over in the plenary room.
But I'll stick around here for a few
minutes for anyone who's just hanging out.
Thank you again and great job.
Thank you Richard.